<listitem>
    <para>
        SSSD supports two representations for specifying the debug level. The
        simplest is to specify a decimal value from 0-9, which represents
        enabling that level and all lower-level debug messages. The more
        comprehensive option is to specify a hexadecimal bitmask to enable or
        disable specific levels (such as if you wish to suppress a level).
    </para>
    <para>
        Please note that each SSSD service logs into its own log
        file. Also please note that enabling <quote>debug_level</quote>
        in the <quote>[sssd]</quote> section only enables debugging just
        for the sssd process itself, not for the responder or provider
        processes. The <quote>debug_level</quote> parameter should be
        added to all sections that you wish to produce debug logs from.
    </para>
    <para>
        In addition to changing the log level in the config file using
        the <quote>debug_level</quote> parameter, which is persistent, but
        requires SSSD restart, it is also possible to change the debug level
        on the fly using the
        <citerefentry>
            <refentrytitle>sss_debuglevel</refentrytitle>
            <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
        </citerefentry>
        tool.
    </para>
    <para>
        Currently supported debug levels:
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>0</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0010</emphasis>:
         Fatal failures. Anything that would prevent SSSD from starting up or
         causes it to cease running.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>1</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0020</emphasis>:
         Critical failures. An error that doesn't kill SSSD, but one that
         indicates that at least one major feature is not going to work
         properly.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>2</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0040</emphasis>: Serious failures. An error announcing
         that a particular request or operation has failed.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>3</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0080</emphasis>: Minor failures. These are the errors that
         would percolate down to cause the operation failure of 2.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>4</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0100</emphasis>: Configuration settings.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>5</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0200</emphasis>: Function data.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>6</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x0400</emphasis>: Trace messages for operation functions.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>7</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x1000</emphasis>: Trace messages for internal control
         functions.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>8</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x2000</emphasis>: Contents of function-internal variables
         that may be interesting.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>9</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x4000</emphasis>: Extremely low-level tracing information.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>9</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x20000</emphasis>: Performance and statistical data,
         please note that due to the way requests are processed internally the
         logged execution time of a request might be longer than it actually
	 was.
    </para>
    <para>
         <emphasis>10</emphasis>,
         <emphasis>0x10000</emphasis>: Even more low-level libldb tracing
         information. Almost never really required.
    </para>
    <para>
        To log required bitmask debug levels, simply add their numbers together
        as shown in following examples:
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis>Example</emphasis>: To log fatal failures, critical failures,
        serious failures and function data use 0x0270.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis>Example</emphasis>: To log fatal failures, configuration
        settings, function data, trace messages for internal control functions
        use 0x1310.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis>Note</emphasis>: The bitmask format of debug levels was
        introduced in 1.7.0.
    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis>Default</emphasis>: 0x0070 (i.e. fatal, critical and serious
        failures; corresponds to setting 2 in decimal notation)
    </para>
</listitem>
