<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<reference>
<title>SSSD Manual pages</title>
<refentry>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/upstream.xml" />

    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>sss-certmap</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo class="manual">File Formats and Conventions</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv id='name'>
        <refname>sss-certmap</refname>
        <refpurpose>SSSD Certificate Matching and Mapping Rules</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsect1 id='description'>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            The manual page describes the rules which can be used by SSSD and
            other components to match X.509 certificates and map them to
            accounts.
        </para>
        <para>
            Each rule has four components, a <quote>priority</quote>, a
            <quote>matching rule</quote>, a <quote>mapping rule</quote> and a
            <quote>domain list</quote>. All components are optional. A missing
            <quote>priority</quote> will add the rule with the lowest priority.
            The default <quote>matching rule</quote> will match certificates with
            the digitalSignature key usage and clientAuth extended key usage. If
            the <quote>mapping rule</quote> is empty the certificates will be
            searched in the userCertificate attribute as DER encoded binary. If
            no domains are given only the local domain will be searched.
        </para>
        <para>
            To allow extensions or completely different style of rule the
            <quote>mapping</quote> and <quote>matching rules</quote> can
            contain a prefix separated with a ':' from the main part of the
            rule. The prefix may only contain upper-case ASCII letters and
            numbers. If the prefix is omitted the default type will be used
            which is 'KRB5' for the matching rules and 'LDAP' for the mapping
            rules.
        </para>
        <para>
            The 'sssctl' utility provides the 'cert-eval-rule' command to check
            if a given certificate matches a matching rules and how the output
            of a mapping rule would look like.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='components'>
        <title>RULE COMPONENTS</title>
    <refsect2 id='priority'>
        <title>PRIORITY</title>
        <para>
            The rules are processed by priority while the number '0' (zero)
            indicates the highest priority. The higher the number the lower is
            the priority. A missing value indicates the lowest priority. The
            rules processing is stopped when a matched rule is found and no
            further rules are checked.
        </para>
        <para>
            Internally the priority is treated as unsigned 32bit integer, using
            a priority value larger than 4294967295 will cause an error.
        </para>
        <para>
            If multiple rules have the same priority and only one of the related
            matching rules applies, this rule will be chosen. If there are
            multiple rules with the same priority which matches, one is chosen
            but which one is undefined. To avoid this undefined behavior either
            use different priorities or make the matching rules more specific
            e.g. by using distinct &lt;ISSUER&gt; patterns.
        </para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2 id='match'>
        <title>MATCHING RULE</title>
        <para>
            The matching rule is used to select a certificate to which the
            mapping rule should be applied. It uses a system similar to the one
            used by <quote>pkinit_cert_match</quote> option of MIT Kerberos. It
            consists of a keyword enclosed by '&lt;' and '&gt;' which identified
            a certain part of the certificate and a pattern which should be
            found for the rule to match. Multiple keyword pattern pairs can be
            either joined with '&amp;&amp;' (and) or '&#124;&#124;' (or).
        </para>
        <para>
            Given the similarity to MIT Kerberos the type prefix for this rule
            is 'KRB5'. But 'KRB5' will also be the default for <quote>matching
            rules</quote> so that "&lt;SUBJECT&gt;.*,DC=MY,DC=DOMAIN" and
            "KRB5:&lt;SUBJECT&gt;.*,DC=MY,DC=DOMAIN" are equivalent.
        </para>
        <para>
            The available options are:
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SUBJECT&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        With this a part or the whole subject name of the
                        certificate can be matched. For the matching POSIX
                        Extended Regular Expression syntax is used, see regex(7)
                        for details.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        For the matching the subject name stored in the
                        certificate in DER encoded ASN.1 is converted into a
                        string according to RFC 4514. This means the most
                        specific name component comes first. Please note that
                        not all possible attribute names are covered by RFC
                        4514. The names included are 'CN', 'L', 'ST', 'O',
                        'OU', 'C', 'STREET', 'DC' and 'UID'. Other attribute
                        names might be shown differently on different platform
                        and by different tools. To avoid confusion those
                        attribute names are best not used or covered by a
                        suitable regular-expression.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SUBJECT&gt;.*,DC=MY,DC=DOMAIN
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Please note that the characters "^.[$()|*+?{\" have a
                        special meaning in regular expressions and must be
                        escaped with the help of the '\' character so that they
                        are matched as ordinary characters.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SUBJECT&gt;^CN=.* \(Admin\),DC=MY,DC=DOMAIN$
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;ISSUER&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        With this a part or the whole issuer name of the
                        certificate can be matched. All comments for
                        &lt;SUBJECT&gt; apply her as well.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;ISSUER&gt;^CN=My-CA,DC=MY,DC=DOMAIN$
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;KU&gt;key-usage</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This option can be used to specify which key usage
                        values the certificate should have. The following values
                        can be used in a comma separated list:
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem><para>digitalSignature</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>nonRepudiation</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>keyEncipherment</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>dataEncipherment</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>keyAgreement</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>keyCertSign</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>cRLSign</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>encipherOnly</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>decipherOnly</para></listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        A numerical value in the range of a 32bit unsigned
                        integer can be used as well to cover special use cases.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;KU&gt;digitalSignature,keyEncipherment
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;EKU&gt;extended-key-usage</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This option can be used to specify which extended key
                        usage the certificate should have. The following value
                        can be used in a comma separated list:
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem><para>serverAuth</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>clientAuth</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>codeSigning</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>emailProtection</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>timeStamping</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>OCSPSigning</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>KPClientAuth</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>pkinit</para></listitem>
                            <listitem><para>msScLogin</para></listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Extended key usages which are not listed above can be
                        specified with their OID in dotted-decimal notation.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;EKU&gt;clientAuth,1.3.6.1.5.2.3.4
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        To be compatible with the usage of MIT Kerberos this
                        option will match the Kerberos principals in the PKINIT
                        or AD NT Principal SAN as &lt;SAN:Principal&gt; does.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN&gt;.*@MY\.REALM
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:Principal&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the Kerberos principals in the PKINIT or AD NT
                        Principal SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:Principal&gt;.*@MY\.REALM
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:ntPrincipalName&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the Kerberos principals from the AD NT Principal
                        SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:ntPrincipalName&gt;.*@MY.AD.REALM
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:pkinit&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the Kerberos principals from the PKINIT SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:ntPrincipalName&gt;.*@MY\.PKINIT\.REALM
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:dotted-decimal-oid&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Take the value of the otherName SAN component given by
                        the OID in dotted-decimal notation, interpret it as
                        string and try to match it against the regular
                        expression.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:1.2.3.4&gt;test
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:otherName&gt;base64-string</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Do a binary match with the base64 encoded blob against
                        all otherName SAN components. With this option it is
                        possible to match against custom otherName components
                        with special encodings which could not be treated as
                        strings.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:otherName&gt;MTIz
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:rfc822Name&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the value of the rfc822Name SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:rfc822Name&gt;.*@email\.domain
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:dNSName&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the value of the dNSName SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:dNSName&gt;.*\.my\.dns\.domain
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:x400Address&gt;base64-string</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Binary match the value of the x400Address SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:x400Address&gt;MTIz
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:directoryName&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the value of the directoryName SAN. The same
                        comments as given for &lt;ISSUER&gt; and &lt;SUBJECT&gt;
                        apply here as well.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:directoryName&gt;.*,DC=com
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:ediPartyName&gt;base64-string</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Binary match the value of the ediPartyName SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:ediPartyName&gt;MTIz
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:uniformResourceIdentifier&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the value of the uniformResourceIdentifier SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:uniformResourceIdentifier&gt;URN:.*
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:iPAddress&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the value of the iPAddress SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:iPAddress&gt;192\.168\..*
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>&lt;SAN:registeredID&gt;regular-expression</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Match the value of the registeredID SAN as
                        dotted-decimal string.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: &lt;SAN:registeredID&gt;1\.2\.3\..*
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2 id='map'>
        <title>MAPPING RULE</title>
        <para>
            The mapping rule is used to associate a certificate with one or more
            accounts. A Smartcard with the certificate and the matching private
            key can then be used to authenticate as one of those accounts.
        </para>
        <para>
            Currently SSSD basically only supports LDAP to lookup user
            information (the exception is the proxy provider which is not of
            relevance here). Because of this the mapping rule is based on LDAP
            search filter syntax with templates to add certificate content to
            the filter. It is expected that the filter will only contain the
            specific data needed for the mapping and that the caller will embed
            it in another filter to do the actual search. Because of this the
            filter string should start and stop with '(' and ')' respectively.
        </para>
        <para>
            In general it is recommended to use attributes from the certificate
            and add them to special attributes to the LDAP user object. E.g. the
            'altSecurityIdentities' attribute in AD or the 'ipaCertMapData'
            attribute for IPA can be used.
        </para>
        <para>
            This should be preferred to read user specific data from the
            certificate like e.g. an email address and search for it in the LDAP
            server. The reason is that the user specific data in LDAP might
            change for various reasons would break the mapping. On the
            other hand it would be hard to break the mapping on purpose for a
            specific user.
        </para>
	<para>
            The default <quote>mapping rule</quote> type is 'LDAP' which can be
            added as a prefix to a rule like e.g.
            'LDAP:(userCertificate;binary={cert!bin})'. There is an extension
            called 'LDAPU1' which offer more templates for more flexibility. To
            allow older versions of this library to ignore the extension the
            prefix 'LDAPU1' must be used when using the new templates in a
            <quote>mapping rule</quote> otherwise the old version of this
            library will fail with a parsing error. The new templates are
            described in section <xref linkend="map_ldapu1"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
            The templates to add certificate data to the search filter are based
            on Python-style formatting strings. They consist of a keyword in
            curly braces with an optional sub-component specifier separated by a
            '.' or an optional conversion/formatting option separated by a '!'.
            Allowed values are:
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{issuer_dn[!((ad|ad_x500)|ad_ldap|nss_x500|(nss|nss_ldap))]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the full issuer DN converted to a
                        string according to RFC 4514. If X.500 ordering (most
                        specific RDN comes last) an option with the '_x500'
                        prefix should be used.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The conversion options starting with 'ad_' will use
                        attribute names as used by AD, e.g. 'S' instead of 'ST'.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The conversion options starting with 'nss_' will use
                        attribute names as used by NSS.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The default conversion option is 'nss', i.e. attribute
                        names according to NSS and LDAP/RFC 4514 ordering.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (ipacertmapdata=X509:&lt;I&gt;{issuer_dn!ad}&lt;S&gt;{subject_dn!ad})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_dn[!((ad|ad_x500)|ad_ldap|nss_x500|(nss|nss_ldap))]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the full subject DN converted to
                        string according to RFC 4514. If X.500 ordering (most
                        specific RDN comes last) an option with the '_x500'
                        prefix should be used.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The conversion options starting with 'ad_' will use
                        attribute names as used by AD, e.g. 'S' instead of 'ST'.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The conversion options starting with 'nss_' will use
                        attribute names as used by NSS.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The default conversion option is 'nss', i.e. attribute
                        names according to NSS and LDAP/RFC 4514 ordering.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (ipacertmapdata=X509:&lt;I&gt;{issuer_dn!nss_x500}&lt;S&gt;{subject_dn!nss_x500})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{cert[!(bin|base64)]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the whole DER encoded certificate
                        as a string to the search filter. Depending on the
                        conversion option the binary certificate is either
                        converted to an escaped hex sequence '\xx' or base64.
                        The escaped hex sequence is the default and can e.g. be
                        used with the LDAP attribute 'userCertificate;binary'.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (userCertificate;binary={cert!bin})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_principal[.short_name]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the Kerberos principal which is
                        taken either from the SAN used by pkinit or the one used
                        by AD. The 'short_name' component represents the first
                        part of the principal before the '@' sign.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (|(userPrincipal={subject_principal})(samAccountName={subject_principal.short_name}))
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_pkinit_principal[.short_name]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the Kerberos principal which is
                        given by the SAN used by pkinit. The 'short_name'
                        component represents the first part of the principal
                        before the '@' sign.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (|(userPrincipal={subject_pkinit_principal})(uid={subject_pkinit_principal.short_name}))
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_nt_principal[.short_name]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the Kerberos principal which is
                        given by the SAN used by AD. The 'short_name' component
                        represent the first part of the principal before the '@'
                        sign.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (|(userPrincipalName={subject_nt_principal})(samAccountName={subject_nt_principal.short_name}))
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_rfc822_name[.short_name]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the string which is stored in the
                        rfc822Name component of the SAN, typically an email
                        address. The 'short_name' component represents the first
                        part of the address before the '@' sign.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (|(mail={subject_rfc822_name})(uid={subject_rfc822_name.short_name}))
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_dns_name[.short_name]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the string which is stored in the
                        dNSName component of the SAN, typically a fully-qualified host name.
                        The 'short_name' component represents the first
                        part of the name before the first '.' sign.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (|(fqdn={subject_dns_name})(host={subject_dns_name.short_name}))
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_uri}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the string which is stored in the
                        uniformResourceIdentifier component of the SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (uri={subject_uri})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_ip_address}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the string which is stored in the
                        iPAddress component of the SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (ip={subject_ip_address})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_x400_address}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the value which is stored in the
                        x400Address component of the SAN as escaped hex
                        sequence.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (attr:binary={subject_x400_address})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_directory_name[!((ad|ad_x500)|ad_ldap|nss_x500|(nss|nss_ldap))]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the DN string of the value which
                        is stored in the directoryName component of the SAN.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (orig_dn={subject_directory_name})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_ediparty_name}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the value which is stored in the
                        ediPartyName component of the SAN as escaped hex
                        sequence.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (attr:binary={subject_ediparty_name})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_registered_id}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the OID which is stored in the
                        registeredID component of the SAN as a dotted-decimal
                        string.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: (oid={subject_registered_id})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    <refsect3 id='map_ldapu1'>
        <title>LDAPU1 extension</title>
        <para>
            The following templates are available when using the 'LDAPU1'
            extension:
        </para>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{serial_number[!(dec|hex[_ucr])]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the serial number of the
                        certificate. By default it will be printed as a
			hexadecimal number with lower-case letters.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        With the formatting option '!dec' the number will be
                        printed as decimal string. The hexadecimal output can
                        be printed with upper-case letters ('!hex_u'), with a
                        colon separating the hexadecimal bytes ('!hex_c') or
                        with the hexadecimal bytes in reverse order ('!hex_r').
                        The postfix letters can be combined so that e.g.
                        '!hex_uc' will produce a colon-separated hexadecimal
                        string with upper-case letters.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: LDAPU1:(serial={serial_number})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_key_id[!hex[_ucr]]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the subject key id of the
                        certificate. By default it will be printed as a
			hexadecimal number with lower-case letters.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The hexadecimal output can
                        be printed with upper-case letters ('!hex_u'), with a
                        colon separating the hexadecimal bytes ('!hex_c') or
                        with the hexadecimal bytes in reverse order ('!hex_r').
                        The postfix letters can be combined so that e.g.
                        '!hex_uc' will produce a colon-separated hexadecimal
                        string with upper-case letters.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: LDAPU1:(ski={subject_key_id})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{cert[!DIGEST[_ucr]]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the hexadecimal digest/hash of
                        the certificate where DIGEST must be replaced with the
                        name of a digest/hash function supported by OpenSSL,
                        e.g. 'sha512'.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The hexadecimal output can
                        be printed with upper-case letters ('!sha512_u'), with a
                        colon separating the hexadecimal bytes ('!sha512_c') or
                        with the hexadecimal bytes in reverse order
                        ('!sha512_r'). The postfix letters can be combined so
                        that e.g. '!sha512_uc' will produce a colon-separated
                        hexadecimal string with upper-case letters.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: LDAPU1:(dgst={cert!sha256})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{subject_dn_component[(.attr_name|[number]]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add an attribute value of a component
                        of the subject DN, by default the value of the most
                        specific component.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        A different component can be selected by either
                        attribute name, e.g. {subject_dn_component.uid} or by
                        position, e.g. {subject_dn_component.[2]} where
                        positive numbers start counting from the most specific
                        component and negative numbers start counting from the
                        least specific component. Attribute name and the
                        position can be combined as e.g.
                        {subject_dn_component.uid[2]} which means that the name
                        of the second component must be 'uid'.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: LDAPU1:(uid={subject_dn_component.uid})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{issuer_dn_component[(.attr_name|[number]]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add an attribute value of a component
                        of the issuer DN, by default the value of the most
                        specific component.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        See 'subject_dn_component' for details about the
                        attribute name and position specifiers.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: LDAPU1:(domain={issuer_dn_component.[-2]}.{issuer_dn_component.dc[-1]})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>{sid[.rid]}</term>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This template will add the SID if the corresponding
                        extension introduced by Microsoft with the OID
                        1.3.6.1.4.1.311.25.2 is available. With the '.rid'
                        selector only the last component, i.e. the RID, will be
                        added.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: LDAPU1:(objectsid={sid})
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </refsect3>
    </refsect2>
    <refsect2 id='domains'>
        <title>DOMAIN LIST</title>
        <para>
            If the domain list is not empty users mapped to a given certificate
            are not only searched in the local domain but in the listed domains
            as well as long as they are know by SSSD. Domains not know to SSSD
            will be ignored.
        </para>
    </refsect2>
    </refsect1>
</refentry>
</reference>
