<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<reference>
<title>SSSD Manual pages</title>
<refentry>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/upstream.xml" />

    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>sssd_krb5_locator_plugin</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv id='name'>
        <refname>sssd_krb5_locator_plugin</refname>
        <refpurpose>Kerberos locator plugin</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsect1 id='description'>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            The Kerberos locator plugin
            <command>sssd_krb5_locator_plugin</command> is used by libkrb5 to
            find KDCs for a given Kerberos realm. SSSD provides such a plugin to
            guide all Kerberos clients on a system to a single KDC. In general
            it should not matter to which KDC a client process is talking to.
            But there are cases, e.g. after a password change, where not all
            KDCs are in the same state because the new data has to be replicated
            first. To avoid unexpected authentication failures and maybe even
            account lockings it would be good to talk to a single KDC as long as
            possible.
        </para>
        <para>
            libkrb5 will search the locator plugin in the libkrb5 sub-directory
            of the Kerberos plugin directory, see plugin_base_dir in
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>krb5.conf</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
            for details. The plugin can only be disabled by removing the plugin
            file. There is no option in the Kerberos configuration to disable
            it. But the SSSD_KRB5_LOCATOR_DISABLE environment variable can be
            used to disable the plugin for individual commands. Alternatively
            the SSSD option krb5_use_kdcinfo=False can be used to not generate
            the data needed by the plugin. With this the plugin is still
            called but will provide no data to the caller so that libkrb5 can
            fall back to other methods defined in krb5.conf.
        </para>
        <para>
            The plugin reads the information about the KDCs of a given realm
            from a file called <filename>kdcinfo.REALM</filename>. The file
            should contain one or more DNS names or IP addresses either in
            dotted-decimal IPv4 notation or the hexadecimal IPv6 notation.
            An optional port number can be added to the end separated with
            a colon, the IPv6 address has to be enclosed in squared brackets
            in this case as usual. Valid entries are:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>kdc.example.com</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>kdc.example.com:321</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>1.2.3.4</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>5.6.7.8:99</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>2001:db8:85a3::8a2e:370:7334</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>[2001:db8:85a3::8a2e:370:7334]:321</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            SSSD's krb5 auth-provider which is used by the IPA and AD providers
            as well adds the address of the current KDC or domain controller
            SSSD is using to this file.
        </para>
        <para>
            In environments with read-only and read-write KDCs where clients are
            expected to use the read-only instances for the general operations
            and only the read-write KDC for config changes like password changes
            a <filename>kpasswdinfo.REALM</filename> is used as well to identify
            read-write KDCs. If this file exists for the given realm the content
            will be used by the plugin to reply to requests for a kpasswd or
            kadmin server or for the MIT Kerberos specific master KDC. If the
            address contains a port number the default KDC port 88 will be used
            for the latter.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='notes'>
        <title>NOTES</title>
        <para>
            Not all Kerberos implementations support the use of plugins. If
            <command>sssd_krb5_locator_plugin</command> is not available on
            your system you have to edit /etc/krb5.conf to reflect your
            Kerberos setup.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the environment variable SSSD_KRB5_LOCATOR_DEBUG is set to any
            value debug messages will be sent to stderr.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the environment variable SSSD_KRB5_LOCATOR_DISABLE is set to any
            value the plugin is disabled and will just return
            KRB5_PLUGIN_NO_HANDLE to the caller.
        </para>
        <para>
            If the environment variable SSSD_KRB5_LOCATOR_IGNORE_DNS_FAILURES
            is set to any value plugin will try to resolve all DNS names
            in kdcinfo file. By default plugin returns KRB5_PLUGIN_NO_HANDLE
            to the caller immediately on first DNS resolving failure.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/seealso.xml" />

</refentry>
</reference>
