<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<reference>
<title>SSSD Manual pages</title>
<refentry>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/upstream.xml" />

    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>sssd-ad</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
        <refmiscinfo class="manual">File Formats and Conventions</refmiscinfo>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv id='name'>
        <refname>sssd-ad</refname>
        <refpurpose>SSSD Active Directory provider</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsect1 id='description'>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            This manual page describes the configuration of the AD provider
            for
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>sssd</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
            For a detailed syntax reference, refer to the <quote>FILE FORMAT</quote> section of the
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>sssd.conf</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry> manual page.
        </para>
        <para>
            The AD provider is a back end used to connect to an Active
            Directory server. This provider requires that the machine be
            joined to the AD domain and a keytab is available.
        </para>
        <para>
            The AD provider supports connecting to Active Directory 2008 R2
            or later. Earlier versions may work, but are unsupported.
        </para>
        <para>
            The AD provider is able to provide identity information and
            authentication for entities from trusted domains as well. Currently
            only trusted domains in the same forest are recognized.
        </para>
        <para>
            The AD provider accepts the same options used by the
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>sssd-ldap</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry> identity provider and the
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>sssd-krb5</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry> authentication provider with some exceptions described
            below.
        </para>
        <para>
            However, it is neither necessary nor recommended to set these
            options. The AD provider can also be used as an access, chpass and
            sudo provider. No configuration of the access provider is required
            on the client side.
        </para>
        <para>
            By default, the AD provider will map UID and GID values from the
            objectSID parameter in Active Directory. For details on this, see
            the <quote>ID MAPPING</quote> section below. If you want to
            disable ID mapping and instead rely on POSIX attributes defined in
            Active Directory, you should set
            <programlisting>
ldap_id_mapping = False
            </programlisting>
            In order to retrieve users and groups using POSIX attributes from trusted
            domains, the AD administrator must make sure that the POSIX attributes
            are replicated to the Global Catalog.
        </para>
        <para>
            Users, groups and other entities served by SSSD are always treated as
            case-insensitive in the AD provider for compatibility with Active
            Directory's LDAP implementation.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='configuration-options'>
        <title>CONFIGURATION OPTIONS</title>
        <para>Refer to the section <quote>DOMAIN SECTIONS</quote> of the
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>sssd.conf</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry> manual page for details on the configuration of an SSSD domain.
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_domain (string)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Specifies the name of the Active Directory domain.
                            This is optional. If not provided, the
                            configuration domain name is used.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            For proper operation, this option should be
                            specified as the lower-case version of the long
                            version of the Active Directory domain.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The short domain name (also known as the NetBIOS
                            or the flat name) is autodetected by the SSSD.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_server, ad_backup_server (string)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The comma-separated list of
                            hostnames of the AD servers to which SSSD should
                            connect in order of preference. For more
                            information on failover and server redundancy, see
                            the <quote>FAILOVER</quote> section.
                            This is optional if autodiscovery is enabled.
                            For more information on service discovery, refer
                            to the <quote>SERVICE DISCOVERY</quote> section.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_hostname (string)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Optional. May be set on machines where the
                            hostname(5) does not reflect the fully qualified
                            name used in the Active Directory domain to
                            identify this host.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            This field is used to determine the host principal
                            in use in the keytab. It must match the hostname
                            for which the keytab was issued.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_enable_dns_sites (boolean)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Enables DNS sites - location based
                            service discovery.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            If true and service discovery (see Service
                            Discovery paragraph at the bottom of the man page)
                            is enabled, the SSSD will first attempt to discover
                            the Active Directory server to connect to using the
                            Active Directory Site Discovery and fall back to
                            the DNS SRV records if no AD site is found. The
                            DNS SRV configuration, including the discovery
                            domain, is used during site discovery as well.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: true
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_access_filter (string)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This option specifies LDAP access control
                            filter that the user must match in order
                            to be allowed access. Please note that the
                            <quote>access_provider</quote> option must be
                            explicitly set to <quote>ad</quote> in order
                            for this option to have an effect.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The option also supports specifying different
                            filters per domain or forest. This
                            extended filter would consist of:
                            <quote>KEYWORD:NAME:FILTER</quote>.
                            The keyword can be either <quote>DOM</quote>,
                            <quote>FOREST</quote> or missing.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            If the keyword equals to <quote>DOM</quote>
                            or is missing, then <quote>NAME</quote> specifies
                            the domain or subdomain the filter applies to.
                            If the keyword equals to <quote>FOREST</quote>,
                            then the filter equals to all domains from the
                            forest specified by <quote>NAME</quote>.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Multiple filters can be separated with the
                            <quote>?</quote> character, similarly to how
                            search bases work.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            The most specific match is always used. For
                            example, if the option specified filter
                            for a domain the user is a member of and a
                            global filter, the per-domain filter would
                            be applied.  If there are more matches with
                            the same specification, the first one is used.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Examples:
                        </para>
                        <programlisting>
# apply filter on domain called dom1 only:
dom1:(memberOf=cn=admins,ou=groups,dc=dom1,dc=com)

# apply filter on domain called dom2 only:
DOM:dom2:(memberOf=cn=admins,ou=groups,dc=dom2,dc=com)

# apply filter on forest called EXAMPLE.COM only:
FOREST:EXAMPLE.COM:(memberOf=cn=admins,ou=groups,dc=example,dc=com)
                        </programlisting>
                        <para>
                            Default: Not set
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_enable_gc (boolean)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            By default, the SSSD connects to the Global
                            Catalog first to retrieve users from trusted
                            domains and uses the LDAP port to retrieve
                            group memberships or as a fallback. Disabling
                            this option makes the SSSD only connect to
                            the LDAP port of the current AD server.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Please note that disabling Global Catalog support
                            does not disable retrieving users from trusted
                            domains. The SSSD would connect to the LDAP port
                            of trusted domains instead. However, Global
                            Catalog must be used in order to resolve
                            cross-domain group memberships.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: true
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>ad_gpo_access_control (string)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            This option specifies the operation mode for
                            GPO-based access control functionality:
                            whether it operates in disabled mode, enforcing
                            mode, or permissive mode. Please note that the
                            <quote>access_provider</quote> option must be
                            explicitly set to <quote>ad</quote> in order for
                            this option to have an effect.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            GPO-based access control functionality uses GPO
                            policy settings to determine whether or not a
                            particular user is allowed to logon to a particular
                            host.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            NOTE: If the operation mode is set to enforcing, it
                            is possible that users that were previously allowed
                            logon access will now be denied logon access (as
                            dictated by the GPO policy settings). In order to
                            facilitate a smooth transition for administrators,
                            a permissive mode is available that will not enforce
                            the access control rules, but will evaluate them and
                            will output a syslog message if access would have
                            been denied. By examining the logs, administrators
                            can then make the necessary changes before setting
                            the mode to enforcing.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            There are three supported values for this option:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        disabled: GPO-based access control rules
                                        are neither evaluated nor enforced.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        enforcing: GPO-based access control
                                        rules are evaluated and enforced.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        permissive: GPO-based access control
                                        rules are evaluated, but not enforced.
                                        Instead, a syslog message will be
                                        emitted indicating that the user would
                                        have been denied access if this option's
                                        value were set to enforcing.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: permissive
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>dyndns_update (boolean)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Optional. This option tells SSSD to automatically
                            update the Active Directory DNS server with
                            the IP address of this client. The update is
                            secured using GSS-TSIG. As a consequence, the
                            Active Directory administrator only needs to
                            allow secure updates for the DNS zone. The IP
                            address of the AD LDAP connection is used for
                            the updates, if it is not otherwise specified
                            by using the <quote>dyndns_iface</quote> option.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            NOTE: On older systems (such as RHEL 5), for this
                            behavior to work reliably, the default Kerberos
                            realm must be set properly in /etc/krb5.conf
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: true
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>dyndns_ttl (integer)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The TTL to apply to the client DNS record when updating it.
                            If dyndns_update is false this has no effect. This will
                            override the TTL serverside if set by an administrator.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: 3600 (seconds)
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>dyndns_iface (string)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Optional. Applicable only when dyndns_update
                            is true. Choose the interface whose IP address
                            should be used for dynamic DNS updates.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: Use the IP address of the AD LDAP connection
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>dyndns_refresh_interval (integer)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            How often should the back end perform periodic DNS update in
                            addition to the automatic update performed when the back end
                            goes online.
                            This option is optional and applicable only when dyndns_update
                            is true.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: 86400 (24 hours)
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>dyndns_update_ptr (bool)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Whether the PTR record should also be explicitly
                            updated when updating the client's DNS records.
                            Applicable only when dyndns_update is true.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: True
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>dyndns_force_tcp (bool)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Whether the nsupdate utility should default to using
                            TCP for communicating with the DNS server.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Default: False (let nsupdate choose the protocol)
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>

                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/override_homedir.xml" />
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/homedir_substring.xml" />

                <varlistentry>
                    <term>krb5_use_enterprise_principal (boolean)</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Specifies if the user principal should be treated
                            as enterprise principal. See section 5 of RFC 6806
                            for more details about enterprise principals.
                        </para>

                        <para>
                            Default: true
                        </para>
                        <para>
                             Note that this default differs from the
                             traditional Kerberos provider back end.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/failover.xml" />

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/service_discovery.xml" />

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/ldap_id_mapping.xml" />

    <refsect1 id='example'>
        <title>EXAMPLE</title>
        <para>
            The following example assumes that SSSD is correctly
            configured and example.com is one of the domains in the
            <replaceable>[sssd]</replaceable> section. This example shows only
            the AD provider-specific options.
        </para>
        <para>
<programlisting>
[domain/EXAMPLE]
id_provider = ad
auth_provider = ad
access_provider = ad
chpass_provider = ad

ad_server = dc1.example.com
ad_hostname = client.example.com
ad_domain = example.com
</programlisting>
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='notes'>
        <title>NOTES</title>
        <para>
            The AD access control provider checks if the account is expired.
            It has the same effect as the following configuration of the LDAP
            provider:
<programlisting>
access_provider = ldap
ldap_access_order = expire
ldap_account_expire_policy = ad
</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            However, unless the <quote>ad</quote> access control provider
            is explicitly configured, the default access provider is
            <quote>permit</quote>.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

	<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/seealso.xml" />

</refentry>
</reference>
