<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<reference>
<title>SSSD Manual pages</title>
<refentry>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/upstream.xml" />

    <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>sssd_krb5_localauth_plugin</refentrytitle>
        <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
    </refmeta>

    <refnamediv id='name'>
        <refname>sssd_krb5_localauth_plugin</refname>
        <refpurpose>Kerberos local authorization plugin</refpurpose>
    </refnamediv>

    <refsect1 id='description'>
        <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
        <para>
            The Kerberos local authorization plugin
            <command>sssd_krb5_localauth_plugin</command> is used by libkrb5 to
            either find the local name for a given Kerberos principal or to
            check if a given local name and a given Kerberos principal relate
            to each other.
        </para>
        <para>
            SSSD handles the local names for users from a remote source and can
            read the Kerberos user principal name from the remote source as
	    well. With this information SSSD can easily handle the mappings
            mentioned above even if the local name and the Kerberos principal
            differ considerably.
        </para>
        <para>
            Additionally with the information read from the remote source SSSD
            can help to prevent unexpected or unwanted mappings in case the
	    user part of the Kerberos principal accidentally corresponds to a
            local name of a different user. By default libkrb5 might just strip
            the realm part of the Kerberos principal to get the local name
            which would lead to wrong mappings in this case.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <refsect1 id='configuration'>
        <title>CONFIGURATION</title>
        <para>
            The Kerberos local authorization plugin must be enabled explicitly
            in the Kerberos configuration, see
            <citerefentry>
                <refentrytitle>krb5.conf</refentrytitle>
                <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>.
            SSSD will create a config snippet with the content like e.g.
<programlisting>
[plugins]
 localauth = {
  disable = an2ln
  module = sssd:/usr/lib64/sssd/modules/sssd_krb5_localauth_plugin.so
 }
</programlisting>
            automatically in the SSSD's public Kerberos configuration snippet
            directory. If this directory is included in the local Kerberos
            configuration the plugin will be enabled automatically.
        </para>
        <para>
            This configuration snippet also disables the
            <command>an2ln</command> module provided by MIT Kerberos if SSSD is
            configured to use the AD or IPA provider. In those environments
            <command>sssd_krb5_localauth_plugin</command> can reliably map the
            system user names to Kerberos principals. A fallback to
            <command>an2ln</command> might cause issues in environments where
            users have the privilege to create Kerberos principals on their own
            which might collide with names of other users used in the system.
            Other modules provided by MIT Kerberos, e.g.
            <command>k5login</command> are not affected.
        </para>
        <para>
            Note: If using <quote>auth_provider = krb5</quote> then
            <command>sssd_krb5_localauth_plugin</command> is not used, therefore
            the above text is not applicable.
        </para>
    </refsect1>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="include/seealso.xml" />

</refentry>
</reference>
